

Kipngetich Ruto

Born 19th of October 1993 kipngetichruto73@gmail.co m

+254716350600

CERTIFICATES

Cisco Certified Network Associate (CCNA)

The Cisco Certified
Networking Associate
(CCNA) certification is the
perfect starting point for
emerging network
engineers looking to
enhance their foundational
networking knowledge. It
teaches students to install,
configure, troubleshoot and
operate LAN, WAN and dial
access services for
medium-sized networks.
Dec 2018

ASSOCIATIONS

South Rift Evangelistic Team

Vice-Chairperson

LANGUAGES

Swahili

Spoken: Fluent • Written: Fluent

English

Spoken: Fluent • Written: Fluent

INTRO

I have about 3 years of work experience in retail industry, holding different roles. This was achieved due to my self-driven character and nature of always yearning to give the best results while maintaining high standards of professionalism.

I have worked as a cash officer which involves entire cash handling processes. I therefore best understand what a dynamic and busy environment entails.

I have long-life learning abilities that has enable me to continue learning in my desired career path. I have done online self-study on Introduction to Cybersecurity, responsive web design, and currently doing a course on python offered by Udemy.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Developer Freelance • Oct 2020 - Present

Cash Officer

Tusker Mattresses Limited • Feb 2020 - Oct 2020

- Prepare and issue Till Dose to cashiers and ensure that they have confirmed it and inserted the same in the system.
- Ensure that all Tills are in proper working condition and they have been restarted before the cashiers start their operations.
- Reconcile previous day sales, balance the Sales statement, and prepare the Sales/Change banking for Collection by CIT.
- The cash officer is solely responsible for the management of Branch float, petty cash, and all customer cheques that have been received and also going to the bank.
- Arranging cashier's shift, offs, and leave.
- Placing orders for change, providing the cashiers with the necessary Change, and also Outsourcing coins and loose when there is a shortage.
- Making regular drops and ensuring all money is taken to the CDM and a minimum amount is retained at the till to assist the cashier in providing change to customers.
- Supervising the cashiers as they operate the CDM and deposits all the money and a receipt to confirm the same issued to the cash officer.
- Supervising change of shifts conveniently by the cashiers and parkers during the day by running a CID report and ensuring the tills are ready for the next Shift.
- Preparing cashier worksheet/ Cashier variance worksheet, printing the statement, giving previous day statements to the manager or admin for confirmation and ensuring the same is ready to be sent to HQ the next morning.

Cashier

Tusker Mattresses Limited • May 2018 - Jan 2020

Duties and Responsibilities

- Receive payment by cash, credit cards, vouchers, credit notes, Mpesa.
- Issue receipts, refunds, or change due to customers.
- Count money in cash drawers at the beginning of shifts to ensure that amounts are correct and that there is adequate change.
- Maintain clean and orderly checkout areas.
- Compute and record totals of transactions.



- Calculate total payments received during a time period, and reconcile this with total sales.
- Sort, count and wrap currency and coins.

Sales Assistant

Tusker Mattresses Limited • Dec 2017 - Apr 2018

Duties and Responsibilities

- Stocktaking.
- Checking for stoke-out and placing Local Purchase Order.
- Analyzing how products are moving so as to help the company put in strategies on how to maximize profits while meeting the set targets.
- Giving customers guidance about the use of the products.
- Arranging products on the shelves.

Achievements

- I have been able to surpass targets assigned to my sections with above 25% growth in all the three sections I have been assign to work at.
- Come up with a list of items in my sections to enable me tract sales and avoid stock-outs.

Intern IT

Ministry of Labour And East African Community Affairs • May 2016 - Jul 2016

- Cable clipping.
- Troubleshooting of user computers and servers.
- Installation of software on user computers such as operating systems.
- Replacement of hardware peripheries such as rams, hard disks.
- Training staff on the use of some IT equipment and software

EDUCATION



B.Sc. Mathematics and Computer Science Kenyatta University • Jan 2013 - Jan 2017

SPECIALIZATION

I took applied Math option with computer science as I specialized in my 3rd year.

EXTRA-CURRICULAR

I was a Member and the Vice-chairperson in a group call South Rift Evangelistic Team.



Certificate of Secondary Education Longisa High School • Jan 2009 - Jan 2012



Certificate of Primary Education Kimenderit Primary School • Jan 2000 - Jan 2008



SKILLS

Reporting Payment collection Cash management (company) Troubleshooting
Time management Teamwork PHP JavaScript
Github (or other software version management systems) HTML IT support
Customer service Customer relations Time management Teamwork
Cash management Presentation skills Product knowledge Order processing
Direct sales Customer relations Customer service Time management

<u>Teamwork</u> <u>Negotiation</u> <u>Ability to coordinate</u> <u>General ledger</u> <u>Leadership skills</u>

Conflict management and resolution Accounting IT-systems (use of)

Ability to coordinate Leadership skills Data analysis

Conflict management and resolution Experimentation Ability to coordinate

Accounting IT-systems (use of) IT support

Computer, laptop maintenance and repair

Database query languages (SQL, others) Bootstrap

Agile and Lean methodologies Troubleshooting

 $\underline{\mathsf{IT}\ \mathsf{equipment}\ \mathsf{installation}\ \mathsf{and}\ \mathsf{configuration}}\quad \underline{\mathsf{Ability}\ \mathsf{to}\ \mathsf{coordinate}}\quad \underline{\mathsf{HTML}}\quad \underline{\mathsf{CSS}}$

PHP Python JavaScript JavaScript



HOBBIES



Listening to soft music

Travelling

Reading motivational books



LINKS